<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yundung.ch/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yundung.ch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-05-27T07:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA" /><published>2025-05-02T14:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-02T14:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-this-reflection">Why This Reflection?</h2>

<p>After four blogposts exploring the <strong>history</strong>, <strong>mission</strong>, and <strong>technological foundation</strong> of the <strong>Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC)</strong> and its platform <strong>BUDA</strong>, I want to end this series on a more personal note. My previous entries aimed to present BDRC’s work in a clear and objective way. This final post, by contrast, is written from my own perspective as a potential user of BUDA. <em>What does it actually feel like to use this platform?</em> What are its <strong>strengths</strong>, its <strong>challenges</strong>, and its <strong>possibilities</strong> for someone like me?</p>

<p>This reflection is shaped by my own position, which sits at a unique intersection, I am a <strong>student of Central Asian (Tibetan) Studies</strong> as well as <strong>Digital Humanities</strong>. I am digitally interested and already familiar with some Tibetan Buddhist literature. At the same time, I am a Swiss-born Tibetan, fluent in colloquial Tibetan, with basic reading skills. English is the more natural language for me when doing research. And beyond all that, I am also a <strong>practicing Buddhist</strong>, which means my interest in BUDA is both <strong>scholarly and personal</strong>. These overlapping identities shape my experience of the platform in ways that are sometimes <em>empowering</em>, sometimes <em>overwhelming</em>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="first-impressions">First Impressions</h2>

<p>Opening <strong>BUDA</strong> for the first time, I felt genuinely impressed. The interface is clean, the speed is excellent, and - importantly - it is <strong>openly accessible</strong>. There is no need to register or log in to start exploring. This reflects <strong>BDRC’s values of openness and inclusivity</strong>.</p>

<p>At the same time, the <strong>simplicity of the design</strong> masks the platform’s <strong>underlying complexity</strong>. BUDA is not just a library of scanned texts. It is</p>
<ul>
  <li>a sophisticated metadata system</li>
  <li>a digital preservation platform, and</li>
  <li>a research tool
all at once. It took me some time to grasp how everything is structured and how best to search for the materials I was looking for.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="between-language-practice-and-research">Between Language, Practice, and Research</h2>

<p>My experience of using BUDA is shaped by the <strong>intersection</strong> of my roles as a <em>practitioner</em> and a <em>researcher</em>, as well as by my <em>linguistic situation</em>.</p>

<p>As someone raised in Switzerland in a Tibetan family, I can speak and understand Tibetan fluently, but my ability to <strong>read texts</strong> is still a work in progress. I can read Tibetan, but not yet well enough to fully engage with most canonical works. This makes the <strong>English interface essential</strong> for me.</p>

<p>However, one issue I encountered is that <strong>searching for texts</strong> often requires inputting <strong>keywords in Tibetan</strong>, and even more specifically in <strong>Wylie transliteration</strong>. Typing in <strong>Tibetan script</strong> is already a challenge for me, and <strong>Wylie</strong> requires a precise knowledge of how Tibetan syllables are spelled - which can be difficult if your literacy is still developing.</p>

<p>BUDA has recently introduced a feature called <strong>“Tibetan in phonetics”</strong>, which is a <strong>promising step toward more accessible searching</strong>. If the platform could one day fully support <strong>phonetic Romanized Tibetan</strong> (<em>i.e., how we pronounce words</em>), that would be a <strong>real breakthrough for users like me</strong>. This would be especially valuable given that <strong>typing in Wylie</strong> requires perfect spelling knowledge.</p>

<p>However, using <strong>phonetic Tibetan</strong> also poses challenges, since there is currently <strong>no widely accepted standard</strong> for how Tibetan sounds should be rendered in Roman letters. Despite this, even a <strong>flexible or adaptive phonetic search option</strong> would significantly <strong>lower the barrier</strong> for users like me and make BUDA more accessible to a <strong>broader audience</strong>.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-phonetics-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-phonetics-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-phonetics-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-09-phonetics.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Search Query for Tröma Nakmo (Tib. ཁྲོས་མ་ནག་མོ་, Wyl. khros ma nag mo) in BUDA
</div>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="https://www.rigpawiki.org/images/1/12/Troma_Nagmo_Statue-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="https://www.rigpawiki.org/images/1/12/Troma_Nagmo_Statue-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="https://www.rigpawiki.org/images/1/12/Troma_Nagmo_Statue-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="https://www.rigpawiki.org/images/1/12/Troma_Nagmo_Statue.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Image of Tröma Nagmo, a feminine embodiment of wisdom, from [Rigpa Wiki](https://www.rigpawiki.org/index.php?title=Tröma_Nakmo_(Dudjom))
</div>

<p>As a <strong>Buddhist practitioner</strong>, I would begin by going directly to the <a href="https://library.bdrc.io/tradition/bo/?type%5B0%5D=Instance&amp;language%5B0%5D=LangBo&amp;sortBy=firstScanSyncDate_desc"><strong>“Tibetan Tradition”</strong></a> section on BUDA’s homepage. From there, I usually select a specific <strong>lineage</strong>, for example, the <strong>Kagyu school</strong>.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-tibetan-traditions-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-tibetan-traditions-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-09-tibetan-traditions-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-09-tibetan-traditions.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    "Tibetan Traditions" in BUDA
</div>

<p>Because I already have some background knowledge of key figures and works in this tradition, I can navigate the material with more confidence. I know what to look for and can recognize texts that interest me. But I wonder how someone like a fellow Swiss-born Tibetan, with less experience in Buddhist studies, might find their way on the platform. Without some basic context, BUDA’s structure and terminology could be a bit challenging at first.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="strengths-and-limitations">Strengths and Limitations</h2>

<p>There is much to appreciate in <strong>BUDA</strong>. The quality of <strong>digital scans is excellent</strong>, the <strong>metadata is detailed and carefully structured</strong>, and the <strong>inclusion of traditional classifications</strong> helps situate texts within the wider Tibetan literary landscape. Being able to explore entire collections organized by tradition, author, or even geographic origin is remarkable. As a <em>student</em> and <em>practitioner</em>, this feels like a gift.</p>

<p>And yet, there are limits to what I can currently do. While I have a basic understanding of how linked open data works and why metadata is important, I am not yet technically skilled enough to use BUDA’s more advanced research tools such as SPARQL queries or the API. I see the potential, but it lies just beyond my current abilities.</p>

<p>At the same time, I believe BUDA could become even more accessible if BDRC provided additional support materials, especially short tutorials or video guides that walk users through the most important search queries step by step. While I am aware that BDRC already organizes webinars and classes (such as the live demo and training session for BUDA 2.0 announced <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/introducing-buda-2-0-join-us-for-a-demo-of-the-new-site/">here</a>), I think it would be incredibly helpful to make a shorter recording of such sessions available afterward.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="final-thoughts-a-platform-that-inspires-growth">Final Thoughts: A Platform That Inspires Growth</h2>

<p>BUDA is more than just a digital text repository. It’s a platform that encourages learning and growth. It has shown me both what I know and what I still want to explore, helping me experience Tibetan Buddhist heritage in a more tangible way while guiding me toward deeper knowledge.</p>

<p>While I’m excited by the possibilities BUDA offers, I’m also aware of my own linguistic and technical limits that sometimes make the platform feel challenging. For me, BUDA is a bridge between cultural heritage and technology, between past and future, and between personal belief and academic study. I hope it continues to grow in ways that support scholars, Tibetans, digital learners, and spiritual seekers alike.</p>

<p>This brings my five-part blog series on the digitization of Tibetan Buddhist texts to a close.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Thank you for reading!</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="read-all-of-the-blog-posts-here">Read all of the blog posts here:</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</a> (this post)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="digitization" /><category term="buddhist-texts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fifth blogpost out of five]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship" /><published>2025-04-25T18:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-25T18:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-LTWA-1-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-LTWA-1-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-LTWA-1-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/bdrc-07-LTWA-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Photograph taken on February 19, 2024, at the "Tibetan Books and Manuscripts Library" division of the Library of Tibetan Works and Archives (LTWA) in Dharamsala. The image shows shelves of traditional Tibetan manuscripts.
</div>

<p>What does it mean to digitize sacred texts responsibly? In an age where digital tools can enhance access and analysis like never before, there is also a growing recognition that such innovations must be guided by deep cultural understanding. The <a href="https://library.bdrc.io"><strong>Buddhist Digital Archives</strong> (BUDA)</a> platform, developed by the <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/"><strong>Buddhist Digital Resource Center</strong> (BDRC)</a>, is a insightful example of how technology can be aligned with the values and traditions of the communities it serves.</p>

<p>As outlined in the previous two blog posts, BUDA represents an advanced digital repository. In the present blogpost, the focus shifts to its role as a dynamic framework that carefully balances cutting-edge innovation with cultural and scholarly stewardship. Through close collaboration with Tibetan custodians, scholars, and monastic institutions, BUDA ensures that digital preservation upholds and reinforces, rather than disrupts, the traditional functions, meanings, and organizational structures of Buddhist texts.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="cultural-and-scholarly-stewardship-as-the-foundation">Cultural and Scholarly Stewardship as the Foundation</h3>

<p>At the heart of BUDA lies a commitment to <strong>cultural sensitivity</strong> and <strong>collaborative knowledge-building</strong>. BDRC does not impose an external structure onto Tibetan literary traditions. Instead, it digitizes and shares <strong>entire archives</strong>, preserving collections in the order and form maintained by Tibetan custodians themselves. This approach safeguards the <strong>integrity of complex textual traditions</strong>, ensuring that the original cultural and organizational context remains intact.</p>

<p>BDRC’s team collaborates closely with <strong>monastic communities</strong>, <strong>traditional archivists</strong>, and <strong>Buddhist scholars</strong>, who offer essential expertise in local cataloging practices and textual lineages. Their involvement is central to the creation of meaningful metadata and culturally accurate classifications, allowing BUDA to reflect the internal logic of Tibetan knowledge systems.</p>

<p>A notable illustration of this stewardship is BDRC’s ongoing collaboration with the <a href="https://tibetanlibrary.org/"><strong>Library of Tibetan Works and Archives</strong> (LTWA)</a> in Dharamsala, India. Together, they have digitally preserved hundreds of rare and previously unpublished manuscripts from LTWA’s Manuscripts Division. Texts that were once accessible only onsite. This project involved meticulous cataloging and high-quality digitization to preserve not only the texts but also unique features such as rubrication (traditional red ink highlights) and detailed colophons that reveal valuable historical and cultural context.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>

<ul>
  <li>Side note: As part of my master’s thesis <a href="/assets/pdf/Yundung%202024_%20Digitizing%20Tibetan%20Buddhist%20Texts.pdf">Digitizing Tibetan Buddhist Texts – An Analysis of Key Tibetan Actors and Their Roles</a>, I conducted interviews with their director and head librarian to understand the motivations behind their digitization efforts, the challenges they face, and the strategies they employ to balance cultural preservation, scholarly accessibility, and technological advancement.</li>
</ul>

<p>By making these materials freely available online, BDRC and LTWA ensure that precious Tibetan cultural heritage is both protected and accessible to scholars and practitioners worldwide. This partnership exemplifies how digital preservation can honor traditional custodianship while enhancing global knowledge sharing.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="technology-in-service-of-tradition">Technology in Service of Tradition</h3>

<p>While BUDA employs state-of-the-art technologies, such as <strong>high-resolution imaging</strong>, <strong>linked open data</strong>, and an <strong>open-source infrastructure</strong><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, these tools are never ends in themselves. They are designed to support, rather than override, the traditional uses and meanings of the texts.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“BDRC digitizes endangered Buddhist manuscripts for long-term preservation and creates digital tools to support access and research.” 
— <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/programs/">Buddhist Digital Resource Center</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>For example, BUDA’s image-based approach produces <strong>faithful digital facsimiles</strong>, capturing physical features such as <strong>script styles</strong>, <strong>page layout</strong>, and <strong>marginalia</strong>. These details are crucial not only for <strong>philological and codicological research</strong> but also for <strong>religious practice</strong>, where the visual form of a manuscript often holds devotional significance.</p>

<p>Moreover, BUDA’s infrastructure is built to be <strong>technically sustainable and interoperable</strong>, ensuring that these resources remain useful across future platforms and scholarly contexts without sacrificing their cultural authenticity.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="access-with-respect">Access with Respect</h3>

<p>One of BUDA’s core principles is <strong>open access</strong>, understood not just as a technical convenience but as an <strong>ethical commitment</strong>. The vast majority of texts on BUDA are freely downloadable, allowing both scholars and members of Buddhist communities worldwide to engage with them. BDRC’s access policies are designed to <strong>maximize availability</strong> while also respecting <strong>legal, ethical, and cultural rights</strong>.</p>

<p>These guidelines were originally developed by <strong>E. Gene Smith</strong> and have been refined over the years with input from legal experts, including Harvard’s Copyright Advisor. BDRC’s access framework serves two distinct but interconnected purposes: to <strong>sustain living traditions by maximizing access to cultural works</strong>, and to <strong>protect the legal and cultural rights of authors, publishers, and tradition holders</strong>.</p>

<p>Where these purposes come into tension, BDRC <strong>prioritizes respect for the rights of content custodians</strong>. It does <strong>not claim copyright</strong> over any text in its archive and <strong>cannot waive copyright</strong> on behalf of others. Instead, it operates with the understanding that the <strong>Buddhist canon and other scriptures belong to the cultures that produced and preserved them</strong>. A large portion of the archive is in the <strong>public domain</strong> and is therefore openly accessible. For copyrighted works, BDRC <strong>restricts access in accordance with international law</strong> and may apply the doctrine of <strong>fair use</strong> in limited cases.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-access-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-access-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-07-access-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/bdrc-07-access.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Types of Restricted Access at BDRC
</div>

<p>In addition to legal considerations, BDRC also <strong>restricts access out of cultural sensitivity</strong>. Some texts, referred to as <strong><em>sealed texts</em></strong>, are considered <strong>esoteric or ritually restricted</strong> by the communities that hold them. Access to these works is limited at the request of the tradition holders to prevent misuse or unintended exposure. Similarly, some materials may be temporarily restricted due to <strong>poor scan quality, incomplete metadata, or other technical limitations</strong>.</p>

<p>BUDA’s platform allows <strong>registered users to freely download full PDFs of open-access works</strong>. Creating an account is free and helps BDRC track use while protecting sensitive content.</p>

<p>In this way, BUDA ensures that <strong>access does not come at the cost of cultural autonomy or ethical responsibility</strong>. Its commitment to <strong><em>access with respect</em></strong> means navigating the complex intersection of preservation, law, technology, and tradition. An approach that sees digitization not just as a technical task, but as a <strong>culturally embedded responsibility</strong>. <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="a-model-for-responsible-digital-preservation">A Model for Responsible Digital Preservation</h3>

<p>The work of BDRC and BUDA exemplifies <strong>responsible digital stewardship</strong>. It is a model that prioritizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>preservation of traditional organization and context</strong>, rather than selective or decontextualized digitization.</li>
  <li><strong>Collaborative creation of metadata</strong> and cataloging systems, informed by those rooted in the culture.</li>
  <li>The use of <strong>digital innovation to support tradition</strong>, not replace it.</li>
  <li>An <strong>open-access ethos</strong>, grounded in cultural respect and legal responsibility.</li>
</ul>

<p>In doing so, BUDA not only supports cutting-edge scholarship but also <strong>empowers Buddhist communities</strong> to sustain their own traditions in the digital age. It shows that the future of textual preservation lies not in mere access or innovation alone, but in the <strong>careful alignment of both</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>BUDA demonstrates that <strong>digital tools can serve tradition</strong> when developed through partnership, humility, and cultural understanding. Its strategies such as preserving whole archives, honoring traditional organization, and providing open yet respectful access offer a roadmap for other digital preservation efforts worldwide.</p>

<p>In a time when digitization is often driven by speed and efficiency, BUDA reminds us that <strong>thoughtfulness, context, and respect</strong> are equally important. Through its model of innovation guided by cultural sensitivity, BUDA ensures that the Dharma is not only preserved, but truly honored in the digital realm.</p>

<h2 id="coming-up-in-the-series">Coming up in the series:</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</a> (this post)</li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/blog/2024/11/27/bdrc-and-the-library-of-tibetan-works-and-archives-collaborate-on-digital-preservation-of-manuscripts/">https://www.bdrc.io/blog/2024/11/27/bdrc-and-the-library-of-tibetan-works-and-archives-collaborate-on-digital-preservation-of-manuscripts/</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://github.com/buda-base/">https://github.com/buda-base/</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/access-policies/">https://www.bdrc.io/access-policies/</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="digitization" /><category term="buddhist-texts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fourth blogpost out of five]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2" /><published>2025-04-18T08:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-18T08:44:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-00.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The BUDA platform interface
</div>

<h2 id="how-to-use-buda">How to Use BUDA</h2>

<h3 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#navigating-buda-search-features-that-empower-research">Navigating BUDA: Search Features that Empower Research</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#person-search-connecting-biographies-and-texts">Person Search: Connecting Biographies and Texts</a></li>
      <li><a href="#place-search-mapping-sacred-geography">Place Search: Mapping Sacred Geography</a></li>
      <li><a href="#topic-search-thematic-pathways-through-complex-traditions">Topic Search: Thematic Pathways through Complex Traditions</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="navigating-buda-search-features-that-empower-research">Navigating BUDA: Search Features that Empower Research</h3>

<p>As outlined in a previous post, BUDA provides a wide range of tools designed to support access, analysis, and discovery: From navigating linked data to using the integrated e-text reader or downloading high-quality digital manuscripts. Building on this foundation, the search functionality plays a central role in locating specific persons, places, or texts within the archive. With its flexible filters, phonetic and multilingual input options, and structured metadata, BUDA’s search interface offers an efficient and precise way to explore the breadth of its collections.</p>

<p>By default, the search function is set to “Versions”, meaning that any query will return results corresponding to specific instances or editions of texts (such as print editions, block prints, or digital scans) and is generally used to search for texts by their titles.</p>

<p>However, by switching to “Advanced Search” in the main search bar, it becomes possible to refine the type of content being queried. On the right-hand side of the search bar, a dropdown menu allows for the selection of specific search categories. These include: <em>Works, Texts, Etexts, Persons, Places, Topics, and Collections</em>. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>

<p>For the purposes of this post, only three of these categories will be introduced: Persons, Places, and Topics. Each serves as a different starting point for exploring BUDA’s organised data and vast digital holdings.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JXq3NVft8RQ?si=hDdBNnYWjiOOhjOn&amp;start=138" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h4 id="person-search-connecting-biographies-and-texts">Person Search: Connecting Biographies and Texts</h4>

<p>BUDA contains detailed biographical records for thousands of individuals important to Buddhist history (including authors, translators, lineage holders, and religious teachers).</p>

<p><em>How to Search</em></p>
<ol>
  <li>Open Advanced Search.</li>
  <li>Select “Persons” from the dropdown menu.</li>
  <li>Enter the name of the individual using one of the following:
    <ul>
      <li>Tibetan script</li>
      <li>Romanized Wylie transliteration</li>
      <li>Phonetic spelling (for example, “Jigme Lingpa” or “Jikmay Lingpa”) <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<ul>
  <li>As an example, BDRC provides a screenshot of a search query for the historical figure <a href="https://treasuryoflives.org/biographies/view/Gampopa-Sonam-Rinchen/3168">Gampopa Sonam Rinchen</a>, a renowned eleventh-century Tibetan scholar and meditation master who played a central role in the development of the Kagyu lineage of Tibetan Buddhism.</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-0-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-0-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-0-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-06-person-0.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    source: BDRC Common Searches - Person Search
</div>

<p>The search engine recognizes various spellings and transliterations, enabling results even with approximate input.</p>

<p><em>What the Results Include</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>Primary person record with life dates and biographical notes</li>
  <li>Associated works, including texts authored, translated, or transmitted</li>
  <li>Relational data, such as links to teachers, students, lineages, and institutions</li>
  <li>Auto-suggest and phonetic matching, supporting flexible search input</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-1-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-1-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-person-1-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-06-person-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    source: BDRC Common Searches - Person Search
</div>

<p><em>Why Use This Filter</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>This search mode supports research on historical figures, spiritual lineages, and the networks involved in the transmission of Buddhist literature.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="place-search-mapping-sacred-geography">Place Search: Mapping Sacred Geography</h4>

<p>BUDA furthermore maintains comprehensive records of locations such as monasteries, sacred sites, and historical regions that have played a role in the development of Buddhist traditions.</p>

<p><em>How to Search</em></p>
<ol>
  <li>Open Advanced Search.</li>
  <li>Select “Places” from the dropdown menu.</li>
  <li>Enter the name of the location using:
    <ul>
      <li>Tibetan script</li>
      <li>Romanized Wylie transliteration</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<ul>
  <li>As an example, I searched for <a href="https://treasuryoflives.org/institution/Derge-Parkhang">Derge Parkhang</a>, the famous printing house established in the eighteenth century, which I spelled phonetically. The search returned various types of results, including both the physical location and scriptures originally printed there.</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-0-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-0-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-0-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-06-place-0.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Place search
</div>

<p><em>What the Results Include</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>Primary place record for a site, town, region, or monastery</li>
  <li>Linked places, such as institutions within the area</li>
  <li>Metadata, including:
    <ul>
      <li>Multilingual place names (Tibetan, Chinese, Sanskrit, etc.)</li>
      <li>Geographic coordinates and interactive maps</li>
      <li>Historical background and descriptions</li>
      <li>Associated persons or organizations</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>To refine the results, I selected the filter <strong>Type → Place</strong>, which narrowed the results down to three entries. The first one is the correct match. Clicking on this result opens a detailed record containing all available metadata and extended properties, including the exact geographic location of Derge Parkhang on the map. see: <a href="http://purl.bdrc.io/resource/G1657">Derge Parkhang on BUDA</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-1-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-1-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-1-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-06-place-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Place search refined
</div>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-2-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-2-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-06-place-2-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-06-place-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Derge Parkhang on the map
</div>

<p><em>Why Use This Filter</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>This filter is designed for research on the geographic distribution of Buddhist institutions, sacred landscapes, and regional historical developments.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="topic-search-thematic-pathways-through-complex-traditions">Topic Search: Thematic Pathways through Complex Traditions</h4>

<p>BUDA enables thematic exploration of Buddhist knowledge, linking doctrinal concepts, ritual practices, and philosophical terms across a wide range of sources.</p>

<p><em>How to Search</em></p>
<ol>
  <li>On the homepage, open the dropdown menu next to the search bar.</li>
  <li>Select “Topics” from the list of filters.</li>
  <li>Enter the topic name, such as:
    <ul>
      <li>A philosophical concept (for example, “emptiness”)</li>
      <li>A ritual or practice</li>
      <li>A doctrinal or scholastic term</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>What the Results Include</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>Tagged records, including texts, digital editions, and related materials</li>
  <li>Faceted filters for refining by language, period, or subject</li>
  <li>Linked topics, providing access to related concepts and themes</li>
  <li>Topic mentions found in titles or textual content</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Why Use This Filter</em></p>
<ul>
  <li>This search mode facilitates thematic research and cross-disciplinary inquiry, helping to navigate complex tradition</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>In the next post, the focus shifts from technical functionality to guiding principles. While BUDA offers powerful tools for searching and accessing Buddhist texts, it is equally defined by the values that shape its development. The fourth blog post explores how the Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC) aligns innovation with cultural responsibility: Highlighting how collaboration, respectful access policies, and traditional knowledge systems are at the heart of its digital stewardship.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="coming-up-in-the-series">Coming up in the series:</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</a> (this post)</li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/buda-user-guide/common-searches/">https://www.bdrc.io/buda-user-guide/common-searches/</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/buda-user-guide/search-filters/">https://www.bdrc.io/buda-user-guide/search-filters/</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="digitization" /><category term="buddhist-texts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Third blogpost out of five]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1" /><published>2025-04-11T11:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-11T11:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-00-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-00.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The BUDA platform interface
</div>

<p>To provide open access to its extensive collection, BDRC developed the <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/buda-archive/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA)</a>, a powerful online platform that serves as a collaborative archive and research tool.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“BUDA is easy, intuitive, and fast. It features a state-of-the-art image viewer, a sophisticated data structure, and an advanced search that places our vast archive and those of our partner institutions right at your fingertips.”</p>

  <p>— <a href="https://youtu.be/JXq3NVft8RQ?si=2tRiYd_DwdOqsC6B&amp;t=28">Buddhist Digital Resource Center</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>BUDA hosts millions of pages of Buddhist texts, combining high-resolution scans of original manuscripts with digitized electronic texts. The platform’s intuitive design offers a range of tools to support research and study, including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Browsing curated collections by tradition, language, or preservation project</li>
  <li><strong>Advanced multi-language search options</strong></li>
  <li><strong>High-resolution image viewer</strong> to examine original manuscripts</li>
  <li><strong>E-text reader</strong> with translation support</li>
  <li>Linked open data structure that connects people, places, texts, and topics</li>
  <li>Downloadable texts for offline use</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-03-tool-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-03-tool-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-03-tool-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-03-tool.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    BUDA's Tools
</div>

<hr />

<h2 id="exploring-the-vast-collection-of-tibetan-and-buddhist-literature-on-buda">Exploring the Vast Collection of Tibetan and Buddhist Literature on BUDA</h2>
<p>BUDA is built as an open-source platform based on open standards, designed for free use and easy access. At its core are two key technologies: the International Image Interoperability Framework (IIIF) and Linked Open Data (LOD).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
<ul>
  <li>IIIF enables BUDA to provide a rich, user-friendly interface for viewing, downloading, annotating, and sharing high-quality images of Buddhist manuscripts</li>
  <li>BUDA’s LOD architecture structures information in a machine-readable, interconnected way, allowing seamless linking and querying across datasets. This not only supports long-term preservation but also creates a dynamic, globally accessible scholarly hub that connects texts, people, places, and historical contexts within Buddhist cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>

<p>This digital platform allows for accessing an extensive collection of Tibetan and Buddhist texts in multiple languages, including Tibetan, Sanskrit, Chinese, Pali, Burmese, and Khmer.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JXq3NVft8RQ?si=sf7P8w8SMl_0uUGx&amp;start=80" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-to-use-buda">How to Use BUDA</h2>

<h3 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#features-for-access-analysis-and-discovery">Features for Access, Analysis, and Discovery</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#utilize-the-search-function">Utilize the Search Function</a></li>
      <li><a href="#explore-linked-data-rebonds">Explore Linked Data (“Rebonds”)</a></li>
      <li><a href="#access-and-download-digital-manuscripts">Access and Download Digital Manuscripts</a></li>
      <li><a href="#make-use-of-the-e-text-reader-and-research-tools">Make Use of the E-Text Reader and Research Tools</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="features-for-access-analysis-and-discovery">Features for Access, Analysis, and Discovery</h3>

<h4 id="utilize-the-search-function">Utilize the Search Function</h4>

<p>The <a href="https://library.bdrc.io">BUDA homepage</a> features a central search bar that supports a wide range of queries. A simple search allows users to enter a keyword directly, such as a title, name, or topic, using either original scripts or transliterations.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-01-search-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-01-search-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-01-search-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-01-search.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    BUDA’s simple search bar on the homepage
</div>

<p>For more precise results, the “Advanced Search” function enables users to specify where to search: within works, texts, e-texts, authors, persons, places, topics, or collections. Search results can be further refined using filters such as language, version, person, place, and subject. A more detailed introduction to these features will follow in the next post. A more detailed introduction to these features will follow in the next post.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-02-search-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-02-search-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-02-search-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-02-search.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    BUDA’s advanced search interface - offering precise filters for searching by work, person, place, and more
</div>

<h4 id="explore-linked-data-rebonds">Explore Linked Data (“Rebonds”)</h4>

<p>BUDA employs a system of Linked Open Data (LOD) to connect related records and facilitate seamless navigation. For example, users can move from a work to its various versions, to the author’s biographical information, to other works by the same person, or even to related topics and places. This interconnected structure helps users explore the broader context of Buddhist texts and their heritage.</p>

<p>BUDA’s LOD schema captures the “who, what, when, and where” of Buddhist cultural heritage. Every person, place, work, and version in the archive is treated as a distinct, richly described entity connected to others in meaningful ways.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Practical Example of “Rebonds” in Action
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Suppose I am viewing a digitized Tibetan manuscript on BUDA. From this record, I can:</p>

<ul>
  <li>🏃‍♂️ Jump to the author’s biography and see their other works</li>
  <li>🧭 Explore different versions or translations of the text</li>
  <li>📍 View related places (such as the monastery where it was written or stored)</li>
  <li>💡 Discover other texts from the same collection, period, or tradition</li>
</ul>

<p>This interconnected approach transforms BUDA from a static archive into a dynamic research environment, supporting both targeted inquiry and open-ended exploration.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Users can assume a broad-scale view of the Linked Open Data from the entire corpus in the archive and draw much broader conclusions regarding the content, circulation, and use of the smaller bodies of texts hosted in the archive.” - <a href="https://digitalorientalist.com/2021/03/03/images-of-the-buda-digital-archives-and-the-future-of-research-using-linked-open-data/">The Digital Orientalist</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="access-and-download-digital-manuscripts">Access and Download Digital Manuscripts</h4>

<p>BUDA offers high-resolution scans of traditional Tibetan texts which are open access; some texts remain sealed or restricted. Registered users can browse these manuscripts page by page in the online viewer and download complete works as PDFs or image files. Non-registered visitors typically have access only to the first and last 20 pages of most texts.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>
To demonstrate how this works, I searched for “Four Noble Truths” using the search bar at the top of the BUDA interface.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-1-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-1-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-1-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The BUDA homepage with “Four Noble Truths” entered into the search bar
</div>

<p>To narrow down the results, I used the filter panel on the left and selected “Woodblock” under Print Method. This helped me find traditional, horizontal woodblock-printed texts rather than modern book-style editions.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-2-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-2-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-2-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The filter menu with “Woodblock” selected under Print Method
</div>

<p>From the refined list of results, I chose the fifth entry, which looked the most relevant.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-3-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-3-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-3-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-3.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The list of search results, highlighting the fifth item
</div>

<p>Clicking on the title opened the manuscript in BUDA’s Viewer, where I could scroll through the scanned pages in high quality. Because I was logged in, I also had the option to download the full text as a PDF or as a set of image files.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-0-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-0-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-0-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-04-manuscript-0.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    The BUDA Viewer showing the scanned manuscript, with the download options visible
</div>

<h4 id="make-use-of-the-e-text-reader-and-research-tools">Make Use of the E-Text Reader and Research Tools</h4>

<p>In addition to scanned images, many works on BUDA are also available as searchable e-texts. This allows for efficient keyword searches, easier navigation, and deeper study of the text content.</p>

<p>To give an example, I entered “Dalai Lama” into the search bar.
Then, under the Etext filter on the left, I selected “has e-text of any quality” to make sure the results would include texts with digital versions. I chose the first result, which is a collected works volume of the Fifth Dalai Lama—not because of the topic, but because its e-text was marked as excellent quality. The only higher level is “best quality.”</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-1-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-1-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-1-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Search for "Dalai Lama" with e-text filter applied
</div>

<p>As seen in the screenshot, clicking the small information icon reveals that the e-text was</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“automatically created with OCR (Optical Character Recognition) and reviewed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is an important detail, because it means the text is clean and searchable, which is essential for scholars and practitioners who rely on precise word searches and tagging.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Side note: BDRC announced the release of <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/blog/2025/03/14/bdrc-announces-the-release-of-ocr-app-for-tibetan/">OCR app for Tibetan</a> on March 14 2025 - A user-friendly tool wgucg converts scanned Tibetan texts into clean, searchable digital text</li>
</ul>

<p>Next, I clicked “Open in Etext Viewer”.</p>

<p>In the upper-right corner of the Viewer, I typed in a keyword in Wylie, the transcription system used for Tibetan. I searched for “rdzogs chen” (<a href="https://www.rigpawiki.org/index.php?title=Dzogchen">Dzogchen</a>), which is a central tradition of teaching in Tibetan Buddhism. This gave me several search results.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-0-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-0-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-0-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/buda-05-etext-0.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    Matched view of scanned page and e-text showing “rdzogs chen” highlighted
</div>

<p>By clicking on one of the hits, the Viewer showed me the corresponding scanned page on the left and the highlighted e-text on the right.</p>

<p>This side-by-side view of the scanned image and the reviewed e-text makes it much easier to study, search, and cross-reference Tibetan manuscripts with precision and confidence.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>The next blog post will provide a detailed overview of BUDA’s advanced search features. It will explain how to search for persons, places, and topics, enabling more precise and focused exploration of the Buddhist text collection. This includes accessing biographical information, mapping sacred locations, and exploring thematic concepts.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="coming-up-in-the-series">Coming up in the series:</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</a> (this post)</li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/buda-archive/">https://www.bdrc.io/buda-archive/</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://digitalorientalist.com/2021/03/03/images-of-the-buda-digital-archives-and-the-future-of-research-using-linked-open-data/">https://digitalorientalist.com/2021/03/03/images-of-the-buda-digital-archives-and-the-future-of-research-using-linked-open-data/</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="https://www.bdrc.io/access-policies/">https://www.bdrc.io/access-policies/</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="digitization" /><category term="buddhist-texts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Second blogpost out of five]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts" /><published>2025-04-04T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-04T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-00-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-00-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-00-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/bdrc-00.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    BDRC Homepage - An Entry Point to Buddhist Digital Texts
</div>

<p>As part of my final project in Digital Humanities, I am writing a five-part blog series exploring the <strong>digitization of Tibetan Buddhist texts</strong>. This topic has shaped not only my academic research, but also my personal journey at the intersection of tradition and technology. It is the continuation of the work I began in my master’s thesis, where I examined the motivations, challenges, and cultural dynamics behind digitization efforts through in-depth interviews.</p>

<p>One organization that stood out throughout my thesis, but that I was unable to include directly due to the lack of an interview, was the <a href="https://www.bdrc.io"><strong>Buddhist Digital Resource Center</strong> (BDRC)</a>. In fact, the absence of a direct exchange with BDRC during my research only increased my curiosity. That is why I have chosen to dedicate my final Digital Humanities project to BDRC: to dive deeper into its history, mission, technological strategies, and cultural impact.</p>

<h2 id="why-bdrc">Why BDRC?</h2>

<p>My <a href="/assets/pdf/Yundung%202024_%20Digitizing%20Tibetan%20Buddhist%20Texts.pdf">thesis</a> showed that digitization is not just a technical task. It is a cultural and ethical one. It involves navigating questions of access, authority, identity, and preservation, and institutions such as BDRC embody these complexities in their entirety. Looking through BDRC’s public <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/news/">news</a> and project updates, it becomes clear how the organization continuously enhances access to rare texts, develops cutting-edge digital tools, and partners with communities and institutions to safeguard and share Tibetan culture globally.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The Buddhist Digital Resource Center is a nonprofit organization dedicated to seeking out, preserving, documenting, and disseminating Buddhist literature. We provide scholars, translators, Buddhist practitioners, and the general public with access to an unparalleled collection of Buddhist texts. Joining digital technology with scholarship, BDRC ensures that the cultural treasures of the Buddhist literary tradition are secure and accessible for generations to come.”
— <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/about-us/">Buddhist Digital Resource Center</a></p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>BDRC began as the <strong>Tibetan Buddhist Resource Center (TBRC)</strong> in 1999, founded by the late <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/people/e-gene-smith/"><strong>E. Gene Smith</strong></a>. After decades of working with Tibetan texts at the Library of Congress, Smith sought to ensure that the vast literary heritage of Tibet, threatened by displacement and globalization, would not be lost. What made his approach unique was his early embrace of digital tools, not just for storage, but for equitable access. His goal was simple but revolutionary: to make Tibetan texts available to everyone, from monks in exile to scholars across the world.</p>

<div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 mb-3">
  <iframe title="Vimeo player" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/241025523?h=2ab2062237" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="from-tbrc-to-bdrc-expanding-the-mission">From TBRC to BDRC: Expanding the Mission</h2>

<p>Since 2016, the center has grown beyond its original Tibetan focus to include Buddhist texts in Pali, Sanskrit, Chinese, and other languages. This evolution reflects a broader trend I observed in my thesis: the digitization of Buddhist texts is being shaped by an increasingly diverse group of actors with different cultural, educational, and technological backgrounds. BDRC’s shift mirrors this landscape and serves as a perfect case study for how digital tools can serve both scholarly and spiritual traditions. While acknowledging this broader scope, this blog series will primarily focus on BDRC’s work with Tibetan Buddhist texts, in order to build on the core themes and insights of my earlier research.</p>

<h2 id="technology-meets-tradition-buda">Technology Meets Tradition: BUDA</h2>

<p>BDRC’s programs fulfill its mission by preserving endangered Buddhist manuscripts, developing digital tools for access and research, and supporting the repatriation and global engagement with Buddhist literary heritage.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-01-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-01-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/bdrc-01-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/bdrc-01.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    BDRC’s Four-Fold Approach to Buddhist Texts
</div>

<p>One of the most impactful outcomes of this mission is <a href="https://www.bdrc.io/buda-archive/"><strong>BUDA</strong> (Buddhist Universal Digital Archive)</a> - BDRC’s flagship digital platform. BUDA provides access to more than 27 million pages of Buddhist texts. It is more than just a digital library - it is a rich metadata ecosystem that supports nuanced textual analysis, multilingual research, and long-term preservation. BUDA represents an ideal example of how digital infrastructure can be used not simply for information storage, but for cultural transmission.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="from-thesis-to-blog">From Thesis to Blog</h2>

<p>In my master’s thesis, I initially assumed that digitization efforts were primarily driven by Western institutions. But through conversations with monastic leaders, librarians, and digital preservation specialists, I came to recognize the vital and often underappreciated role that Tibetan communities and institutions play in shaping these initiatives. This shift in perspective was one of the most meaningful outcomes of my research.</p>

<p>At the same time, the contributions of non-Tibetan organizations remain essential - none more so than the BDRC. Even though I was not able to include BDRC as a case study in my thesis due to the absence of a direct interview, its presence was unmistakable. As a pioneering force and arguably the most influential organization in the field, BDRC has shaped how Tibetan texts are digitized, catalogued, and made accessible. Its work continues to set standards and provide infrastructure that many others, Tibetan and non-Tibetan alike, build upon. That is why this series begins here: to explore BDRC’s role at the heart of the digital preservation of Tibetan Buddhist texts, and to reflect on the broader implications of its work at the intersection of technology, tradition, and global access.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>This opening post lays the foundation for the series ahead. In the next entry, I will turn to BUDA, the platform that powers BDRC’s digital library. I will unpack how BUDA functions: Not just as a technical infrastructure, but as a framework for organizing, linking, and sharing Tibetan texts in a way that supports long-term preservation, scholarly research, and open access. Its design reflects a thoughtful balance between innovation and cultural sensitivity, offering a model for how digital systems can responsibly steward complex textual traditions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="coming-up-in-the-series">Coming up in the series:</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/introduction/">Digitizing the Dharma – Introducing BDRC and the Digital Preservation of Tibetan Buddhist Texts</a> (this post)</li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/BUDA2/">Buddhist Digital Archives (BUDA) in Focus - Part 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/cultural-sensitivity/">Innovation Guided by Cultural Sensitivity – BDRC’s Model of Responsible Digital Stewardship</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2025/conclusion/">A Personal Reflection on Accessing Tibetan Buddhist Texts Digitally on BUDA</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="digitization" /><category term="buddhist-texts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First blogpost out of five]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with custom blockquotes</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with custom blockquotes" /><published>2023-05-12T19:53:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-12T19:53:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/custom-blockquotes/"><![CDATA[<p>This post shows how to add custom styles for blockquotes. Based on <a href="https://github.com/sighingnow/jekyll-gitbook">jekyll-gitbook</a> implementation.</p>

<p>We decided to support the same custom blockquotes as in <a href="https://sighingnow.github.io/jekyll-gitbook/jekyll/2022-06-30-tips_warnings_dangers.html">jekyll-gitbook</a>, which are also found in a lot of other sites’ styles. The styles definitions can be found on the <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio/blob/master/_sass/_base.scss">_base.scss</a> file, more specifically:</p>

<div class="language-scss highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cm">/* Tips, warnings, and dangers */</span>
<span class="nc">.post</span> <span class="nc">.post-content</span> <span class="nt">blockquote</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-tip</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-tip-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-warning</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-warning-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>

  <span class="k">&amp;</span><span class="nc">.block-danger</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nl">border-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="nl">background-color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-bg</span><span class="p">);</span>

    <span class="nt">p</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-text</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="nt">h1</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h2</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h3</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h4</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h5</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nt">h6</span> <span class="p">{</span>
      <span class="nl">color</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nf">var</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="n">global-danger-block-title</span><span class="p">);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A regular blockquote can be used as following:</p>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; This is a regular blockquote</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; and it can be used as usual</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is a regular blockquote
and it can be used as usual</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These custom styles can be used by adding the specific class to the blockquote, as follows:</p>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### TIP</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; A tip can be used when you want to give advice</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; related to a certain content.</span>
{: .block-tip }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-tip">
  <h5 id="tip">TIP</h5>

  <p>A tip can be used when you want to give advice
related to a certain content.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### WARNING</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; This is a warning, and thus should</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; be used when you want to warn the user</span>
{: .block-warning }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-warning">
  <h5 id="warning">WARNING</h5>

  <p>This is a warning, and thus should
be used when you want to warn the user</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="gt">&gt; ##### DANGER</span>
<span class="gt">&gt;</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; This is a danger zone, and thus should</span>
<span class="gt">&gt; be used carefully</span>
{: .block-danger }
</code></pre></div></div>

<blockquote class="block-danger">
  <h5 id="danger">DANGER</h5>

  <p>This is a danger zone, and thus should
be used carefully</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="blockquotes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with custom blockquotes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with table of contents on a sidebar</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/sidebar-table-of-contents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with table of contents on a sidebar" /><published>2023-04-25T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/sidebar-table-of-contents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/sidebar-table-of-contents/"><![CDATA[<p>This post shows how to add a table of contents as a sidebar.</p>

<h2 id="adding-a-table-of-contents">Adding a Table of Contents</h2>

<p>To add a table of contents to a post as a sidebar, simply add</p>
<div class="language-yml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">toc</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">sidebar</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">left</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>to the front matter of the post. The table of contents will be automatically generated from the headings in the post. If you wish to display the sidebar to the right, simply change <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">left</code> to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">right</code>.</p>

<h3 id="example-of-sub-heading-1">Example of Sub-Heading 1</h3>

<p>Jean shorts raw denim Vice normcore, art party High Life PBR skateboard stumptown vinyl kitsch. Four loko meh 8-bit, tousled banh mi tilde forage Schlitz dreamcatcher twee 3 wolf moon. Chambray asymmetrical paleo salvia, sartorial umami four loko master cleanse drinking vinegar brunch. <a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p>

<h3 id="example-of-another-sub-heading-1">Example of another Sub-Heading 1</h3>

<p>Jean shorts raw denim Vice normcore, art party High Life PBR skateboard stumptown vinyl kitsch. Four loko meh 8-bit, tousled banh mi tilde forage Schlitz dreamcatcher twee 3 wolf moon. Chambray asymmetrical paleo salvia, sartorial umami four loko master cleanse drinking vinegar brunch. <a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p>

<h2 data-toc-text="Customizing" id="customizing-your-table-of-contents">Customizing Your Table of Contents</h2>

<p>If you want to learn more about how to customize the table of contents of your sidebar, you can check the <a href="https://afeld.github.io/bootstrap-toc/">bootstrap-toc</a> documentation. Notice that you can even customize the text of the heading that will be displayed on the sidebar.</p>

<h3 id="example-of-sub-heading-2">Example of Sub-Heading 2</h3>

<p>Jean shorts raw denim Vice normcore, art party High Life PBR skateboard stumptown vinyl kitsch. Four loko meh 8-bit, tousled banh mi tilde forage Schlitz dreamcatcher twee 3 wolf moon. Chambray asymmetrical paleo salvia, sartorial umami four loko master cleanse drinking vinegar brunch. <a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p>

<h3 id="example-of-another-sub-heading-2">Example of another Sub-Heading 2</h3>

<p>Jean shorts raw denim Vice normcore, art party High Life PBR skateboard stumptown vinyl kitsch. Four loko meh 8-bit, tousled banh mi tilde forage Schlitz dreamcatcher twee 3 wolf moon. Chambray asymmetrical paleo salvia, sartorial umami four loko master cleanse drinking vinegar brunch. <a href="https://www.pinterest.com">Pinterest</a> DIY authentic Schlitz, hoodie Intelligentsia butcher trust fund brunch shabby chic Kickstarter forage flexitarian. Direct trade <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold-pressed_juice">cold-pressed</a> meggings stumptown plaid, pop-up taxidermy. Hoodie XOXO fingerstache scenester Echo Park. Plaid ugh Wes Anderson, freegan pug selvage fanny pack leggings pickled food truck DIY irony Banksy.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="toc" /><category term="sidebar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of a blog post with table of contents on a sidebar]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with audios</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/audios/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with audios" /><published>2023-04-25T10:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-25T10:25:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/audios</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/audios/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with audios. It supports local audio files.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <audio src="/assets/audio/epicaly-short-113909.mp3" controls="" />

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <audio src="https://cdn.pixabay.com/download/audio/2022/06/25/audio_69a61cd6d6.mp3" controls="" />

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    A simple, elegant caption looks good between video rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all.
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="including" /><category term="audios" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included audios could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with videos</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with videos" /><published>2023-04-24T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-24T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/videos</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/videos/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with videos. It supports local video files.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        

<figure>

  

  <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" autoplay="" controls="" />

  

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        

<figure>

  

  <video src="/assets/video/pexels-engin-akyurt-6069112-960x540-30fps.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls="" />

  

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
    A simple, elegant caption looks good between video rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all.
</div>

<p>It does also support embedding videos from different sources. Here are some examples:</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        

<figure>

  

  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jNQXAC9IVRw" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto" />

  

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        

<figure>

  

  <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/524933864?h=1ac4fd9fb4&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto" />

  

</figure>

    </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="including" /><category term="videos" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included videos could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">displaying beautiful tables with Bootstrap Tables</title><link href="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/tables/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="displaying beautiful tables with Bootstrap Tables" /><published>2023-03-20T18:37:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-20T18:37:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/tables</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yundung.ch/blog/2023/tables/"><![CDATA[<p>Using markdown to display tables is easy. Just use the following syntax:</p>

<div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>| Left aligned | Center aligned | Right aligned |
| :----------- | :------------: | ------------: |
| Left 1       | center 1       | right 1       |
| Left 2       | center 2       | right 2       |
| Left 3       | center 3       | right 3       |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>That will generate:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Left aligned</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Center aligned</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Right aligned</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Left 1</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">center 1</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">right 1</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Left 2</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">center 2</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">right 2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Left 3</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">center 3</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">right 3</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p></p>

<p>It is also possible to use HTML to display tables. For example, the following HTML code will display a table with <a href="https://bootstrap-table.com/">Bootstrap Table</a>, loaded from a JSON file:</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;table</span>
  <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"table"</span>
  <span class="na">data-toggle=</span><span class="s">"table"</span>
  <span class="na">data-url=</span><span class="s">"{{ '/assets/json/table_data.json' | relative_url }}"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;thead&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;tr&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"id"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>ID<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"name"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Item Name<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"price"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Item Price<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;/tr&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/thead&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/table&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<table data-toggle="table" data-url="/assets/json/table_data.json">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th data-field="id">ID</th>
      <th data-field="name">Item Name</th>
      <th data-field="price">Item Price</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
</table>

<p></p>

<p>By using <a href="https://bootstrap-table.com/">Bootstrap Table</a> it is possible to create pretty complex tables, with pagination, search, and more. For example, the following HTML code will display a table, loaded from a JSON file, with pagination, search, checkboxes, and header/content alignment. For more information, check the <a href="https://examples.bootstrap-table.com/index.html">documentation</a>.</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;table</span>
  <span class="na">data-click-to-select=</span><span class="s">"true"</span>
  <span class="na">data-height=</span><span class="s">"460"</span>
  <span class="na">data-pagination=</span><span class="s">"true"</span>
  <span class="na">data-search=</span><span class="s">"true"</span>
  <span class="na">data-toggle=</span><span class="s">"table"</span>
  <span class="na">data-url=</span><span class="s">"{{ '/assets/json/table_data.json' | relative_url }}"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;thead&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;tr&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-checkbox=</span><span class="s">"true"</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/th&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"id"</span> <span class="na">data-halign=</span><span class="s">"left"</span> <span class="na">data-align=</span><span class="s">"center"</span> <span class="na">data-sortable=</span><span class="s">"true"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>ID<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"name"</span> <span class="na">data-halign=</span><span class="s">"center"</span> <span class="na">data-align=</span><span class="s">"right"</span> <span class="na">data-sortable=</span><span class="s">"true"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Item Name<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
      <span class="nt">&lt;th</span> <span class="na">data-field=</span><span class="s">"price"</span> <span class="na">data-halign=</span><span class="s">"right"</span> <span class="na">data-align=</span><span class="s">"left"</span> <span class="na">data-sortable=</span><span class="s">"true"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Item Price<span class="nt">&lt;/th&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;/tr&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;/thead&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/table&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<table data-click-to-select="true" data-height="460" data-pagination="true" data-search="true" data-toggle="table" data-url="/assets/json/table_data.json">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th data-checkbox="true"></th>
      <th data-field="id" data-halign="left" data-align="center" data-sortable="true">ID</th>
      <th data-field="name" data-halign="center" data-align="right" data-sortable="true">Item Name</th>
      <th data-field="price" data-halign="right" data-align="left" data-sortable="true">Item Price</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
</table>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an example of how to use Bootstrap Tables]]></summary></entry></feed>